Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today’s דף *daf* is נ"ח *Nun Chet*
עמוד *amud* נ"ח *Nun Chet*. We pick up, we actually are a
little ahead, we pick up with גופא Gufa. *Gufa* about ten lines
down on נ"ח *Nun Chet* עמוד *amud* נ"ח *Nun Chet*—two dots. So
to remind us what we’ve been talking about, we go through the
list of things that can and cannot be worn on שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbos*, first starting with what cannot,
outside into the street, maybe even into the courtyard because of a
concern it will be worn in the street. And the primary focus
now is things that biblically are considered to be clothing or ornaments,
or you know jewelry, but rabbinically a concern that they’ll be taken
off or they’ll fall off and therefore they’ll come to be carried.
And the most recent issue had to do with something called a
כבול *kvul*, which is either some type of a scarf that went
under the hairnet, and therefore it was debated because a woman wouldn’t
take off her hairnet to expose her hair, but maybe she might
be able to remove her—this scarf or this other cap under the
hairnet without actually exposing her hair or not, so that was a
question, whether that was a concern. And the other approach is that
this כבול *kvul* is something that is worn by a slave, some
type of a—of like a pendant on him or on his clothes
as a—to signify that he—you know, who his master is and that
he is a slave, and there the concern is is that if
it falls off, at least if it falls off of his clothes,
he might come to not want to be seen wearing his clothes
without this—without this insignia on it, so therefore he will remove his
clothes and carry his clothes, and therefore that was the concern. So
we are now going to continue with that from the two dots
from גופא *Gufa*. Thank you. I should mention an interesting debate in
the ראשונים *Rishonim* since we’re talking about slaves. Presumably the slave—well, the
slave is presumably a non-Jewish slave who has had a ברית מילה
*Bris Milah* if he’s a man and gone to the מקווה *mikvah*
and is obligated in מצוות *mitzvos* at the same—to the same level
as women, and therefore he himself has an issue as follow—you know,
to follow the laws, has a—is restricted by the laws of שבת
Shabbos? *Shabbat*, and presumably would follow the rabbinic laws as well. So
therefore, you know, should not be wearing these things on שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat*. But also, you know, the master is commanded למען ינוח שורך
וחמרך... עבדך ואמתך כמוך *lema’an yanucha shorcha vechamorecha... avdecha va’amascha kamocha*,
that your slave and slave-woman should rest as you, and so presumably
and לא lo, תעשה כל מלאכה melakhah אתה ובנך ובתך עבדך ואמתך
*lo ta’aseh kol melachah atah uvincha uvitecha avdecha va’amascha*, do not do
any work, you and your slave, so presumably if the slave does
מלאכה melakhah. *melachah*, in addition to him transgressing, the master also transgresses.
So this is a matter of concern for the master as well.
I should mention that there’s an interesting position of the ראב"ד *Ravad*
who says that that is not the slave that the תורה Torah
*Torah* is commanding you לא תעשה כל מלאכה אתה וכו' ועבדך ואמתך
*lo ta’aseh kol melachah atah etc. ve’avdecha va’amascha* because that slave or
slave-woman is commanded him or herself, so that’s not just commanded through
the master. The same way the minors, you have to make sure
your kids don’t work, but once they’re adults, they’re still your kids,
but that’s not your command to make sure that they don’t work,
that’s their responsibility. So the ראב"ד *Ravad* says the same is true
by slaves, and the תורה Torah *Torah* that says that your slaves
have to—have to rest is talking about people that are—you know, might
be technically your slaves or working for you but they are not
halachically Jewish, they have not gone through the process of מילה *milah*
and טבילה tevilah *tvilah*, and nevertheless, because they’re in your
employ and they’re under your control, you have to make sure that
they rest on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*. Now he says only to the
extent that they’re not doing work for you; they could be doing
work for themselves, but they can’t be doing work for you. So
that’s just an interesting question about what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
talking about. Yeah, Charlie and then Rizzy?
So how do we get from this to the modern concept of
the שבת Shabbat, גוי *Shabbos goy*?
Oh, we’re not going to get right now. Okay, but we will
talk about having a non-Jew do work for you, but that is
when they are not under your, you know, authority and control. This
is not just somebody that’s like your employee, this is somebody that
actually is partly owned in person by you or, you know, in
a—like almost or maybe something like an indentured servant type of a
thing, but it’s not strictly a slave or it’s certainly not the
slave that is according to the ראב"ד *Ravad* that is himself Jewish,
because that would then not be through you he’d be obligated, he’d
be obligated directly, yes.
So if the slaves are obligated the same way as women, Jewish
women,
yes, the ones that have gone through that process of טבילה *tvilah*
and ברית מילה *Bris Milah*, right, right.
But so—but very
often, especially in the Middle Ages, no, this was very relevant because
in the Middle Ages, Jews did own slaves in the Middle Ages—I
mean they had people working for them as well, but they actually
did own slaves, but they were not slaves that halachically had gone
through the מילה *milah* and טבילה *tvilah* process. But in the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara*, yes, but that’s why this discussion was very relevant for
the ראשונים *Rishonim*.
So my question is, why does the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* break down
like
women...
men wear different clothing from women and slaves wear different clothing from
men and women.
Oh, you mean why did it start by saying במה האדם יוצא
and then start with and then subdivide it? Human being. Yeah, I
don't know, I don't know, it's a good question. I mean, they're
going to have to subdivide it anyway, but you know, they are
going to talk about במה אשה יוצאה. bameh ishah yotzeh. Why they
didn't just say... Yeah, but I understand that women wear jewelry to
some...
It's true, but it would have different הלכות, halachos, it would have
different considerations because of the different social norms. So there are going
to be different הלכות halachos for each of those categories. Why put
it in one category, start with one declaration, I don't know, presumably
because these clothing is very gender distinct, you know, very gendered, and
so the assumption that these things are different categories.
Let's continue, I hear the point. Let's just get started a little
bit, okay? גופא. So let's look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר שמואל
יוצא העבד בחותם שבצוארו אבל לא בחותם שבכסותו. Amar Shmuel: yotze ha'eved
bechotam shebetzavaro aval lo bechotam shebechsuto.
A slave can go out, so this is going back to the
statement we ended with yesterday, a slave can go out wearing his
sort of pendant, this seal of identification around his neck, but not
on his garment. And the explanation given for the difference is that
if the one around his neck breaks, so fine, he'll leave it,
he won't do anything, what's he going to do? But if the
one around his garment breaks, he doesn't want to be seen walking
around with a garment that does not have the pendant on it,
he'll get in trouble from his master, better to take off the
garment so he's not seen as though he's you know as though
he's flouting the rule and wearing the garment without it. So we're
concerned that it'll fall off and then he'll come to carry the
garment. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly. יוצא העבד
בחותם שבצוארו אבל לא בחותם שבכסותו. yotze ha'eved bechotam shebetzavaro aval lo
bechotam shebechsuto. He can go out with this with the seal around
his neck but not on his garment. ורמינהו, Ureminhu, I'll ask you
on this, we have a ברייתא braita that contradicts it. It says
לא יצא העבד בחותם שבצוארו ולא בחותם שבכסותו. lo yetze ha'eved bechotam
shebetzavaro velo bechotam shebechsuto. The slave should not go out neither with
the seal around his neck or with it around his garment.
So here it says even around his neck is no good. So
we're going to have to deal with a contradiction about whether he
can go with it around his neck. Now we make another point:
וזה וזה אין מקבלין טומאה. veze veze ein mekablin tumah. Neither of
them can become טמא. tamei. Now again we're constantly moving back and
forth between what's like a vessel or something for שבת, Shabbat. whether
it's מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So why can neither of them become
טמא? tamei? So רש״י Rashi says well look, it's not jewelry because
he's not wearing it because he wants to look nice, right? He's
wearing it because his master makes him wear it, he's wearing it
as a sign of identification that his master is insisting upon. So
it's not jewelry, so therefore it's not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah as
jewelry is. Presumably like you know it's, let me just see, hold
on, let me just check the רש״י's Rashi here.
Right, it's not jewelry. And
also it's not, right, he says it's not jewelry and it's not
like it's not like a vessel that you use, you know, it's
not a it's not a knife, it's not a whatever, it's something
on your body, so it's not being used in any way. But
it's also and it's also not jewelry, so therefore it's not מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tumah, it's not a כלי. kli. Now it's a funny
statement because first of all you could say it is being, it's
being used by the master, you know, being used to identify his
slave, even if we don't say the slave is like willingly using
it, the master is using it. Okay, but maybe having something on
somebody is not considered like a use, you know, you're not actually
like doing something physically with it. But what really bothers me more
than that is, if it's not jewelry, then how's he allowed to
wear it on שבת? Shabbos, Meaning the only concern here about him
wearing it on שבת Shabbat. is that it'll fall off and he'll
come to carry it, right? But it basically assumes that biblically he
is allowed to. So why? It's you either have to call it
jewelry or clothing. But if it's clothing, then why shouldn't it become
טמא? tamei? Unless you say that it's clothing but the only clothing
that becomes טמא tamei is clothing that is out of some type
of a fabric, you know the תורה has that. A clothing that's
out of metal, right, wouldn't become טמא. tamei. I mean you know
what if you had let's say I don't know a suit of
armor, well actually we're going to have something like that, you know.
But what if you had something that's out of a material that
could be טמא tamei but it's not a vessel, it's clothing, and
it's not of fabric either. So maybe that's what the גמרא Gemara
is understanding. But again, I did some research yesterday and I could
not find anybody who discusses this. But to say that it's not
מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because it's not jewelry and at the same
time biblically he's allowed to wear it, to me that becomes very
curious. So you know what's left? If it's not jewelry, what is
it, clothing? So maybe it is clothing but and maybe even though
it's clothing it's not טמא tamei because it's metal and it's not
a fabric. Okay, but that's what we have about this, that it
is not טמא tamei but he's and he's not allowed to wear
it דרבנן derabbanan either on his garment or around his neck. And
the גמרא Gemara will have to deal with that contradiction. And now
we continue. ולא בזוג שבצוארו, Velo bezug shebetzavaro, also he cannot wear
a a bell around his neck. This presumably was a form of
jewelry even for the slave, it's not a form of identification or
form of his slave or a signifier of his slave status, it's
just a jewelry. or around his neck. And the גמרא Gemara, will
have to deal with that contradiction. And now we continue: ולא בזוג
שבצווארו, ve-lo be-zug she-be-tzavaro, also he cannot wear a bell around his
neck. This presumably was a form of jewelry even for the slave,
is not a form of identification or form of his slave's or
a signifier of his slave status, it's just a jewelry. Nevertheless, he
cannot wear it, neither around his
neck, אבל יוצא הוא בזוג שבכסותו, aval yotze hu be-zug she-be-ksuto, he
can wear it if he has these bells woven into his clothing.
וזה וזה מקבלים טומאה, ve-ze ve-ze mekabelin tumah, and this is מקבל
טומאה mekabel tumah because this is jewelry. Jewelry is something that is
מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Okay. ולא תצא. ve-lo tetze.
So that's by the slave. Now moving on to animals.
ולא תצא בהמה לא בחותם שבצווארה ולא בחותם שבכסותה. ve-lo tetze behemah
lo be-chotam she-be-tzavarah ve-lo be-chotam she-be-ksutah. An animal cannot wear a seal,
we discussed that last time. An animal cannot wear tags, identifier tags,
and that seemed to be interestingly by an animal a biblical issue,
that there it was not... it was considered a burden. So again,
I pointed that out yesterday, very strange that by an animal identifier
tags are considered a burden, by a slave they're fundamentally biblically okay,
it's only a rabbinic problem. And I really, I could not find
a discussion about the difference. But anyway, so by an animal cannot
wear the signifier tags. And number two,
ולא בזוג שבכסותה ולא בזוג שבצווארה. ve-lo be-zug she-be-ksutah ve-lo be-zug she-be-tzavarah.
Also cannot wear a bell either around its neck or woven into
some garment you have on the animal. וזה וזה אין מקבלין טומאה.
ve-ze ve-ze ein mekabelin tumah. And by an animal none of it
becomes... is מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because the tag we already said
isn't jewelry, and because the bells we're also basically saying that you
do not have... there is not... we don't recognize this idea of
a jewelry for an animal, which is interesting whether we're sort of
categorically rejecting jewelry for an animal or just saying this isn't functioning
as, we'll see about that in a minute, we'll get to the
case of the animal. Let's first start with the case of the
slave. Okay, so it says like this: So we have a problem
because this said that a slave cannot wear it even around his
neck. How does that reconcile with שמואל'ס Shmuel's statement that he can?
So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא... leima... wait, let's see, here's a
way to reconcile it. הא דעביד ליה רביה הא דעביד ליה לנפשיה.
ha de-avid lei rabeih ha de-avid lei le-nafsheih.
It matters whether the master made it for him and is insisting
he wear it, or he's wearing it himself. Again, hard to understand
for us to understand what... what are the societal realities that a
slave would wear it and his... you know, on his own, on
his own initiative without the master asking. But okay, he's got a
very important master he wants everybody to know whose slave he is,
something of that nature he's wearing it on his own. So that's
the difference. If he's wearing it because his master said, then around
his neck is okay, because we're... because there's no concern he'll take
it off. He won't willingly take it off, he'll get in trouble
with his master, and if it falls off what's he going to
do? He... you know, it's... so that's okay. But if he made
it for himself then we've got a problem, then we're afraid that
he might come to take it off, so the ברייתא braita that
said that he can't wear it around his neck, that's when he
made it for himself. Let's read one... let's see one more line
then take the question. So it says, לא, you don't need... no,
you don't have to make that big of a distinction. אידי ואידי
דעביד ליה רביה. idi ve-idi de-avid lei rabeih. You could actually say
that even in this case his master made it for him. So
normally when his master makes it for him he can wear it
around his neck, no concern he'll take it off, no concern he'll
do anything if it falls off. Why is this ברייתא braita saying
he can't wear it around his neck if his master made him
wear it? וכאן בשל מתכת כאן בשל טינא. ve-kan be-shel matechet kan
be-shel tina. It matters what it's made out of. Is it made
out of plaster or is it made out of metal? Why is
there a difference? Because okay, it fell off on שבת. Shabbat So
you cannot put it back on, but what can you do? You
can pick it up and carry it home. Now why would you
pick it up and carry it home? I mean you're not wearing
it, you'll... if you're caught you'll still get in trouble for not
wearing it, yeah that might be true. But you know, maybe if
it's of a... if it's a valuable thing you'll also get in
trouble for leaving it in the middle of the street. So therefore
it matters, if it's something out of plaster it has no value,
maybe it also would have even shattered when it fell off, so
then we're not concerned. Your master made it for you, you won't
take it off willingly. If it falls off you're going to leave
it where it is, it's worthless. So if your master made it
for you and it's plaster you can wear it. But if your
master made you wear it and it's of metal then we are
concerned, not that you'll take it off willingly, but we're concerned it'll
fall off and then you'll bring it home because you don't want
to get in trouble leaving this valuable metal or leaving metal, you
know, which has value, which is something of... of value in the
middle of the street. And that's why in this ברייתא braita it's
not good, because it is something that you would pick up and
take home. And let me let's just finish the... the point and
then I'll take the questions.
ואמר רב נחמן בר אמי אמר רבה בר אבוה, ve-amar Rav Nachman
bar Ami amar Rabbah bar Avuha, דבר המקפיד עליו רבו, davar ha-makpid
alav rabo, something that the master is מקפיד makpid is like, you
know, what...
what word? Particular? Particular about, right. Something that he cares about and
insists upon, that... now not that you wear it, we're assuming he
always insists that you wear it, but he... he's concerned... he'll be
upset if you don't... if you lose it. So then אין יוצאין
בו. ein yotzin bo. You can't go out with it because we're
afraid you'll drop it and you don't want to get in trouble
with your master. So even though you're trying to keep שבת, Shabbat?
you know, sometimes the fear of בשר ודם basar va-dam especially if
it's a slave master relationship overrides. So therefore if you're going to
get in trouble if you don't bring it home, you can't wear
it on שבת. Shabbat. ודבר שאין מקפיד עליו רבו, ve-davar she-ein makpid
alav rabo, something the master doesn't really care about in terms of
its value—he cares that you wear it but not its value—יוצאין בו,
yotzin bo, you can go out with it, because if you drop
it you will just leave it where it is. it is and
there is no concern. So the case is that the master makes
you wear it, and therefore we're not concerned you'll take it off.
How about being concerned it'll fall off and you'll bring it home
anyway? So there, there's a difference. If it's plaster, no problem. So
that's שמואל Shmuel's case, you're allowed to wear it. If it's metal,
it is a problem. You're not allowed to wear it. Another couple
of statements. First Charlie. No? Paula, you had something from way before.
We talked about something about the norms are going to be different,
and that has something to do with
the הלכה. Halacha. When does הלכה Halacha have anything to do with
the social norms?
Well, it depends on, you know,
well, it does. I mean, I'll just give you a straightforward example.
I mean, there are some הלכות Halachot that are based on that
the
category you put something in is a function of social norms. Like
for example, the idea of בגד איש Beged Ish or בגד אשה,
Beged Isha, what's men's clothing or women's clothing, right, for another biblical
application? So, you know, are pants considered to be men's clothing? So,
you know, obviously for a lot of people don't
wear pants, but it's rarer nowadays to find that argument to be
because it's men's clothing. You know, the argument more nowadays is a
צניעות Tzniut argument, because nowadays if it's so prevalent that women wear
pants, right, it's hard to make—and pants are specifically cut for women—it's
hard to make the argument that they're men's clothing. But when initially,
you know, women started wearing pants, at that stage there was a
period in history where it was seen very much as a man's
garment. And it was seen like, you know, when women started wearing
suits, business suits, right? So initially that was seen, some people reacted
to that as like cross-dressing. Oh, you're trying to dress up like
a man. But now if it becomes social norms change, and therefore
the category of whether it's men's clothing or women's clothing changes. So
here too for שבת, Shabbat. first of all, the rabbinic concern that
you will come to show it to somebody and carry it, well,
that's contexts in which you'll take these things off and show them.
You know, there are contexts in which those realities might change. Also
what's clothing, what's a burden, those types of things are to some
degree a function of the social norms. Now, there is a question,
you are right, particularly around rabbinic edicts, interestingly more than biblical, that
maybe if they specifically, right, the תורה says don't wear men's clothing
or women's clothing, it doesn't define which is which. But it could
be that once the rabbis specifically identified A, B, C, and D,
maybe it gets locked in as that rule even if realities change.
And that's always and that's always a question that's asked, which is
how much are these categories written in stone, these specific applications, not
the category, the specific details written in stone, and how much might
they change when circumstances change? And that gets discussed in every area
of הלכה. Halacha. Okay, so but yeah, there are things that the
facts on the ground, which category you put them in, the categories
are not a priori Platonic categories, they're categories of social constructs. And
therefore they will, you know, change based on changing social reality. Yes,
Michael?
I want to just understand. Are these things, these whatever they were
called,
pendants or whatever they are, are they like...
we're still concerned they're going to fall off or do you believe
wearing these is a big effect? Does it make a difference if
it's likely to fall off or not?
Yeah, so it's similar to the previous question. So again, I don't
know, right, you know, how much are we just identifying a concern.
תוספות Tosfos basically is has other issues and he basically says yeah,
once there's like a concern of some of the things in the
category, we're going to prohibit the whole category. So you know, but
the גמרא, Gemara right, is not clear about that. But the sense
you get is since this is an area of concern, we say
the whole category is no good. But again, these are always things
that are outside the גמרא Gemara before about strings that were woven
into the hair. Does it matter if in this particular circumstance the
specifics are different? Remember the גמרא Gemara, before about the dirty strings?
Okay, so that's always the ongoing question. Let's take a look now
as the גמרא Gemara continues. So now we have this difference about
whether it's of metal or not. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra,
says the גמרא, Gemara you know what, that makes sense. מדקתני זה
וזה אין
מקבלין טומאה,
Midekatani zeh vezeh ein
mekabelin tumah, because we say that both the pendant around his neck
and on his
clothes, the identifier, is not... does not become טמא. Tamei. So אי
אמרת בשלמא של מתכת, Ee amart bishlama shel matechet, if you say
that we're talking about metal types of pendants, so then הני הוא
דלא מקבלי טומאה, Hani hu dela mekabeli tumah, so fine, these aren't
טמא Tamei because like רש"י Rashi says, they're not jewelry, they're not
a כלי, Kli, so therefore they don't become טמא. Tamei. אבל הכלים
דידהו מקבלי טומאה, Aval hakelim didehu mekabeli tumah,
but if you made a vessel out of this material, metal, it
would be. So it's a type of a material that could be
טמא, Tamei, but it's just now it's not been made into a
vessel, it's this pendant which doesn't count as a vessel or as
jewelry. So that makes sense that you have to say it's not
טמא. Tamei. אלא אי אמרת בשל קצינא, Ela ee amart beshel katzina,
if we're talking about plaster type of a pendant, so what do
you mean? הני הוא דלא מקבלי טומאה, Hani hu dela mekabeli tumah,
so because it's a pendant it doesn't become טמא? Tamei? אבל הכלים
דידהו מקבלי טומאה, Aval hakelim didehu mekabeli tumah, if you were to
make a vessel out of plaster it would be טמא? Tamei? That's
not true! והתנן, Vehatnan, we taught in the ברייתא, Braita, which
is really a משנה. Mishna. Okay, כלי אבנים כלי גללים וכלי אדמה
אין
מקבלין טומאה. klei avanim klei glalim veklei adama ein m'kablin tuma. If
you have a vessel made out of stone or out of גללים,
glalim, which is basically dried cow dung, which they would use for
making vessels, and there's actually a word for them, right? Dried cow
dung, buffalo chips, I think, but anyway, but okay, anyway, the כלי
אדמה, klei adama, which means sort of things made out of earth,
dirt, or plaster. Now, how is that different from pottery? Because pottery
is fired in a kiln. This is not fired in a kiln.
So these types of things are not considered הלכתית halachicly כלים kelim
that can become טמא. tamei. And therefore, no matter what vessel you
make out of it, אין מקבלין טומאה. ein m'kablin tuma. They do
not become טמא tamei לא מדברי תורה ולא מדברי סופרים, lo midivrei
Torah velo midivrei sofrim, not biblically or not rabbinically. So obviously if
it has to say that these pendants on slaves are not, do
not become טמא, tamei, then we're obviously talking that they're made out
of a material that usually could be a problem. If they're made
of plaster, then it would be, you know, it would be completely,
you know,
trivial to make that comment. So obviously we're talking that they're made
out of a material like metal that usually could be a problem,
but here it does not become טמא tamei because in this case
it's not considered a vessel. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא שמע
מינה דמתכת, ela shma mina dematachet, so obviously we're talking that they're
made out of metal. שמע מינה, shma mina, that is a good
point. So what have we said until now? The slave cannot wear,
cannot
technically wearing this identifier for an animal to wear a collar with
a tag, the tag if it's only doing its identifying job presumably
is a concern of being considered a burden. For some reason by
the slave wearing this identifier pendant, it's biblically not a burden, it
is some form of clothing, again, strange, because it does not מקבל
טומאה. m'kabel tuma. So it's not מקבל טומאה, m'kabel tuma, it's not
jewelry, it's not a vessel, but somehow it's biblically he can wear
it, let's say it's some form of clothing. But rabbinically there's a
concern that it will fall off and that he will come to
carry his garment or he'll come to pick it up and carry
it. So where those areas are a concern, like on his clothing
or of metal, then he cannot be wearing it. So that's what
we've said so far about the pendant. Now we're going to move
on to the זוג, zug, the bell, which is a form of
jewelry which does become טמא tamei and nevertheless we'll see about a
distinction about when he can or cannot wear it. Yes?
So, you know, why aren't we worried about that for people? In
other words, forget about slaves. No, no, even women, like she can't,
you know, say it's like a pendant she can wear because it's,
you know, we're worried, oh, it's going to fall off, she's going
to...
So we'll see, to some degree we might be. Most valuable things
anyway, most things that are of, you know, we are concerned because
she'll even
take it off and show somebody. So you don't have to say
the additional concern that it will fall off.
But we will see, basically, that is true, that those are, that
those are problems.
I understand. Anyway, it might depend, is it a strap, is it
woven in? You know, so some things that are woven in we're
not as concerned and so on. But yes, basically those are issues.
You know, but most of the time the גמרא Gemara says that
the concern there is that she'll willingly, that she'll take it off,
so you don't have to mention the other concern. But when you
find a case that you think this rule should apply and it's
not applying, you let me know. But what I'm basically saying to
you is, basically we've got those cases covered, they are a problem,
don't worry. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר מר, amar
mar, ולא בזוג שבצוארו. velo bezug she'betzavaro. He can't go out with
a bell around his
neck. אבל יוצא הוא בזוג שבכסותו, aval yotze hu bezug she'bichesuto, it
can be in its garment. So what is the difference? It's jewelry,
it should be okay either way. And it says both are מקבל
טומאה m'kabel tuma because they're considered jewelry. So what's the difference? So
the גמרא Gemara says זוג שבצוארו אמאי לא? zug she'betzavaro amai lo?
Why can't you go out with this bell around the neck? דילמא
מסיק ואתי לאתויי, dilma mipsik va'ate l'atuyei, because of this concern it'll
break and you'll carry it. It's, you know, it's a valuable thing
and therefore it has some value and you'll pick it up and
you'll carry it home. So if that's true, זוג שבכסותו נמי לחוש
דילמא מסיק ואתי לאתויי? zug she'bichesuto nami leichosh dilma mipsik va'ate l'atuyei?
So let's be concerned that even if it's on the garment, it'll
break off and you'll carry it. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא
במאי עסקינן דמיכא בי מומחא, hacha bemai askinan demicha bei mumcha, it
is that we're talking that it's woven in. If it's on the
garment, it's woven in, so there's not a concern that it'll fall
off. You can wear it because it's jewelry, no concern that it'll
fall off, it's woven in the garment. But if it's, you're wearing
it around your neck, we are concerned that it will, that the
strap will break.
In the garment?
No, דמיכא בי מומחא demicha bei mumcha is
the, just means woven. The word, I know מומחא mumcha can mean
an expert, here it just means woven in. וכדרב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע, u'chedrav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
d'amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, כל שארג לא גזרו. kol she'arag
lo gazru. Now
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both point out that this statement is
being used in a very different way. Because if you remember yesterday
or two days ago, it was used to say a concern about
like hair
strings in hair which are tight and are a problem because you
might take it off to go to the מקוה, mikvah, and some
type of a more woven type of a chain in the hair
which is loose and therefore it could be worn because you won't
take it off to go to the מקוה. mikvah. And there we
quoted this statement
כל שארג, kol she'arag, anything woven is not a problem. Now we're
reading this statement in a completely different way. Not about woven strings
in a hair that aren't a חציצה, chatzitza, but we're reading it
as when the bells or other type of jewelry is woven into
a garment, it's not a problem because we're not afraid that it
will fall off. So it's very fascinating because it's a point that
David Weiss Halivni makes about earlier statements of אמוראים Amoraim and how
the גמרא Gemara often is the one that implicitly or explicitly gives
us the context and is it always sort of is that always
necessarily the original context in which it was meant. So here you
have a statement: anything woven isn't a problem, being translated, being implied
in given two very different interpretations in two different גמרות Gemaras about
what that means. Okay, so now we continue. So that's in terms
of the bells, what the difference are. They're jewelry but in one
case we're afraid it'll fall off and not in the other. אמר
מר, Amar Mar, so the master said, continuing down on this in
this ברייתא, Baraita, לא תצא בהמה, Lo tetzei beheimah, an animal can't
go
out, לא בחותם שבצוואר ולא בחותם שבכסותה. lo bechotam she-betzavar velo bechotam
she-biksuta. Cannot wear this signet, this identifying tag on around its neck
or on its garments because for some reason for an animal it's
always considered a burden. It's not a rabbinic problem, it's a
burden. ולא בזוג שבצוואר ולא בזוג שבכסותה. velo bezug she-betzavar velo bezug
she-biksuta. But it also cannot have this jewelry on it or on
its garment. וזה וזה אין מקבלין טומאה. vezeh vezeh ein mekabelin tumah.
And neither of them becomes טמא. tamei. So why can't wear certain
types of jewelry? If you remember there was an earlier debate of
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot whether we have
a whether if you have something that's made for ornament for jewelry
for an animal is it considered a burden or not. Some said
it was always a burden, animals the idea of jewelry in animals
is not something that הלכה halacha recognizes as a normal thing to
be on it. Or some said sometimes it is, sometimes it isn't,
again, it all depends on what the social norms are, whether it's
considered to be out of line, excessive and so on. So here
the bells are considered an animal can't wear it, either jewelry is
always a problem for an animal or this is not this is
going beyond what normally is done and therefore that cannot be worn
on שבת. Shabbat. So that's the שבת Shabbat issue. But then it
says that they're not מקבלין טומאה. mekabelin tumah. So why are they
not מקבלין טומאה? mekabelin tumah? So, okay, maybe the same idea, there's
no concept of jewelry for an animal and therefore it's not considered
a vessel. The owner isn't
using it directly, it's the animal as it were is using it
or it's there for the animal and it's not really considered a
כלי. k'li. But let's see now that the גמרא Gemara will challenge
this.
What is בכסותה biksuta for an animal?
Like רש"י Rashi says like you would put a blanket around a
on a camel or sometimes you put a headdress on certain
a horse you put a headdress on an animal to keep it
warm or to make it look
nice.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, okay, וזוג דבהמה אינו מקבל טומאה? vezug
debeheimah eino mekabel tumah? Is it true that a bell on an
animal does not become טמא? tamei? ורמינהו, ureminhu, but I'll ask you
on this, זוג שבבהמה טמאה ושל דלת טהורה. zug she-bebeheimah tmeiah veshel
delet tehorah. If you have a bell on an animal it's טמאה
tmeiah or can become טמאה tmeiah and on a door it is
טהורה. tehorah. Now why is it טהורה tehorah on a door? Like
you imagine that that's a really functional thing. Maybe it's a doorbell
kept on the outside or something, but you've got some type of
a bell
hung up on a door and you would ring it. So why
should that not become טמא? tamei? It's a vessel, but because it's
attached to a door and a door is attached to a house,
it's מחובר לקרקע. mechubar lekarka. And things that are connected to the
ground are not טמא. tamei. So once it becomes a part of
the house, it also is considered connected to the ground. Is it
always removable? If it's totally removable, like it's hung up on a
nail and you could take it on and off the nail, no,
then it would be a bell and it would be טמא. tamei.
But if it's nailed in, even though in theory you could take
your claw hammer and remove it, at right now it really is
fixed to the door and therefore it is טהור. tahor.
You can ring it on שבת? Shabbat.
No, we're not talking about שבת. Shabbos No, we're not talking about
you can't ring it on שבת.
But if you can open the door.
Okay, so that could very well be a problem, but we're not
talking about שבת. I mean it's in the middle of מסכת שבת,
Masechet Shabbat, but whether that's a שבת problem or not is not
being addressed here.
This wouldn't be טמא? tamei?
Right, or they might stop it up. We've seen cases of stopping
up the you put a stopper in it so it doesn't make
the noise. So you could do that on שבת. We've said that's
been explicitly addressed before in the גמרא Gemara about the bell around
the cow, has it been is it stopped or has it not
been stopped. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. says, or so that's
the ברייתא, Baraita, so you see first off that a בהמה beheimah
bell can become טמא. tamei. So that's a problem with what we
said. Now however it continues: של דלת ועשאו לבהמה. shel delet va'asao
lebeheimah.
You had it banged into the door and then you decided to
make it for the בהמה. beheimah. You got out your hammer, you
removed the nails and you're going now put it around your animal's
neck. טמאה, tmeiah, it's טמאה. tmeiah. Why? Because you have now assigned
it to the animal. So therefore it now is in the category
of an animal's bell and it can become
טמא. tamei. של בהמה ועשאו לדלת. shel behemah va'asao ledelet. If however
it was around the animal's neck and now you've made it on
the door, so then אף על פי שחיברו לדלת, af al pi
she-chibro ledelet, even though you've banged it into the door. and you
fixed it there with nails, טמא. tamei. It is טמא. tamei. Why?
שכל הכלים יורדים לידי טומאה במחשבה ואין עולים מידי טומאתן אלא בשינוי
מעשה. she-kol ha-kelim yordim lidei tum'ah be-machshavah ve-ein olim midei tum'atan ela
be-shinui ma'aseh. All vessels can become considered vessels, that doesn't mean they
become טמא, tamei, they are susceptible for טומאה tum'ah even when you
just think, even when you assign them, you decide now, you know,
they're going to be used for the animal, so it makes it
into an animal bell and an animal bell can become טמא. tamei.
Or you decide you're done making it, so now it's considered a
vessel, so it becomes, gets into the category much easier than it
leaves the category. It gets into the category as soon as you've
decided you're done and it's been assigned and it's been assigned. So
as soon as a bell you've decided you're going to take it
off the door and put it on the animal, now it's an
animal bell, it could become טמא. tamei. However, once it's in the
category, it resists losing its status. Okay, this is what I call
the sticky
principle. So anyway, so therefore, once it's in the category, even though
you've, it's considered a bell that could become טמא, tamei, even though
you banged it into the door, you have not changed its status.
Now, why not? You'll say, I understand you have to do a
שינוי מעשה, shinui ma'aseh, a physical change, but you did a physical
change, you banged it into the door. So the punch is no,
you because you didn't actually change the bell itself, right? You've fixed
it somewhere, you've put holes in like its little eye thing and
you've put a nail in there, but the actual physical bell is
exactly the same way it was before, it's just now attached to
something. So it really resists changing its identity, its easy, or changing
its status of becoming to become טמא. tamei. It's easy to get
that status and it's hard to lose it. Okay, so that is
like the opposite of reputation. Okay, so anyway, so that is, so
that's the story about the bell. So then the question is, what
do you call it? The question is, what do you call it,
about
so how do you deal with the bell of the בהמה? behemah?
Here it says it could become טמא tamei and we said it
could not become טמא. tamei. So what's the story? So the גמרא
Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאית ליה
ענבל והא דלית ליה ענבל. ha d'it leh inbal ve-ha d'leit leh
inbal. It's one is a case that it has a knocker and
the other is a case that it doesn't have a knocker. If
it has a knocker and it actually makes sound as you're the
animal's walking, it becomes טמא. tamei. What's the difference? So ממה נפשך,
mama nafshach, make up your mind says the גמרא. gemara אי מנה
הוא, ei mana hu, if it's a vessel, אף על פי דלית
ליה ענבל, af al pi d'leit leh inbal, then even without the
knocker, like if it's jewelry and we recognize jewelry of an animal
it should be a problem. ואי לאו מנה הוא, ve-ei lav mana
hu, if it's not a vessel so and jewelry doesn't count for
an animal, so ענבל משוי ליה מנה, inbal mashvei leh mana, why
would the knocker make it into a vessel? So אין, in, yes.
כדרבי שמואל בר נחמני ke-darbi Shmuel bar Nachmani like רבי שמואל בר
נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani says אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר
רבי יונתן, amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, דאמר רבי
שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar
Rabbi Yonatan, מניין למשמיע קול בכלי מתכת שהוא טמא? minayin l'mashmia kol
b'kli matechet shehu tamei? How
do you know that metal vessels that make sound, like musical instruments,
how do you know that they are טמא, tamei, they can become
טמא? tamei? שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the verse says, כל דבר אשר יבוא
באש תעבירו באש וטהר, kol davar asher yavo va'esh ta'aviru va'esh ve-taher,
anything that you pass through fire you have to pass through fire
and purify it. Now what was the context here? The context was
when they took the booty from מדין, Midyan, the spoils of war,
and they had in it various vessels. So they bring
these vessels back to משה Moshe and he tells them, here's what
you have to do to make it טהור. tahor.
Or אלעזר הכהן Elazar HaKohen I think it is, right, at that
place? שלעזר she-Elazar who answers them, right? Yeah, that's what, right. Anyway,
so okay, anyway, so אלעזר Elazar so anyway אלעזר Elazar
tells them, he says this is what you have to do, if
you normally put them in fire you put them in fire and
make them טהור, tahor, and if you normally put them in water
you put them in water. Now what's it talking about? The simple
sense of the פסוק pasuk is talking about making them טהור, tahor,
ritually pure. But the problem is is that we never have a
case where fire is part of the process of making something ritually
pure. So therefore חז"ל Chazal tell us we're not talking about making
it ritually pure, we're talking about purifying it from the טרף treif
foods that were cooked in it. And that actually becomes the rabbinic
source, the biblical source for the rabbis of this idea that if
you cook טרף treif foods in a vessel that the vessel cannot
be used until you כשר kasher it. So then it says you
have to pass it through the fire, you know, or put it
in boiling hot water in order to כשר kasher it. That's how
the rabbis read that case. But the simple פשט pshat of the
פסוקים psukim is that it's really talking about ritual purity. And what's
interesting is this גמרא gemara reads it that way. It sort of
brackets the idea that you don't use fire to make things ritually
pure, but it is reading it as an issue about ritual purity.
And therefore it says, so it says things that כל דבר, kol
davar, things, anything that you pass in a fire you have to
purify. And here's the דרשה, drasha, the דרשה drasha is אפילו דיבור
יבוא באש. afilu dibur yavo va'esh. Even words, I thought like that
was God's words, כדברי כאש נאם ה', ke-divrai ka-esh neum Hashem, but
here it says דיבור, dibur, even things that make sound have to
be purified. So not actual speech, but here basically musical instruments. So
they're using this again, they're reading this פסוק pasuk quite interestingly to
פשוטו pshuto that it's not about כשרות kashrut your כלים, kelim, it's
about ritual purity, and because of the word דבר davar they're using
it to say that musical instruments. instruments are also a vessel and
have to be kashered. So according to this, the way therefore, one
way to read the simple way to read this גמרא gemara is
look,
things that are made for a בהמה behemah are not considered vessels.
Ornaments, whatever, they're all the we saw this principle the other day,
the old that or whatever, a week ago, that only if a
vessel is used by a person. So if it's made therefore for
the בהמה behemah and it's not being directly used by the person,
then it's really not a vessel and it cannot become טמא. tamei.
However, there's a special rule that things that make sound, you know,
musical instruments, those are in the category of sound makers and they
become טמא tamei regardless of whether it's for the בהמה behemah or
for me. That simply seems to be what the גמרא gemara is
saying. תוספות, Tosfos, rather than trying to make a new category of
sound makers, says no, actually the point is that it makes sound
and because it's on the בהמה, behemah, it's like you're using it
because why do you put a sound maker on a בהמה? behemah?
So you know where your animal is. So it's like the גמרא
gemara earlier discussed like if you've got a rod that you use
to like, you know, hit your animal and to guide it, that's
considered your using it. If you have a collar that you're using
to control your animal, you're it's your vessel, you're using it for
your animal. So תוספות Tosfos says here too the real point is,
if it's there just as jewelry, you're not using it. But if
it's there to make sound and for you to locate your animal,
then it's your vessel, you're using it. So that's how תוספות Tosfos
reads this case rather than saying that there is a, you know,
totally new category called noise makers.
There is a new category for noise makers, for example if I
buy a trombone from a music shop, first time I used it?
No, we're not talking about we're talking about טבילת כלים tevilas keilim
that we do nowadays which is only about food. We're talking about
the טבילה for right, we're talking here totally about like טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah like תרומה terumah בית המקדש beis hamikdash that type of
stuff.
So a trumpet in the בית המקדש beis hamikdash for instance would
have had to have been טובל? toiveled?
But you know what, you didn't need a פסוק pasuk to tell
you that because that would have just been a כלי, kli, it's
a vessel. The only reason you need the פסוק is to tell
me if it's a musical if it's a bell around a בהמה.
behemah. So then it becomes a question, is it because we're saying
yes musical instruments always need it even if they're for animals, or
is it what תוספות Tosfos says no what we're really just saying
is now it's becomes I'm I'm considered to be the user of
it.
What is the תכלית tachlis of the toy you're making?
Just to make it טהור tahor so it's not a problem if
you have to eat תרומה terumah or go to the בית המקדש.
beis hamikdash. Okay so now the גמרא gemara continues like this. Okay.
So the גמרא gemara says like this, where are we? Okay. במאי
אוקימתא, bimai ukimta, what are we saying that we're talking about this
this bell on the בהמה behemah that it is not does not
become טמא? tamei? דלית ליה ענבל, delais lei inbol, that it doesn't
have a knocker and therefore it's only for ornamentation and therefore it
doesn't become טמא. tamei. אימא מציעתא, ima metziyasa, so if we're talking
about bells without a knocker, let's go back and look at the
earlier case, the middle case, the case about the person wearing the
bell. ולא בזוג שבצוארו, v'lo b'zug shebetzavaro, a person cannot go out
with a bell around his neck, אבל יוצא הוא בזוג שבכסותו, aval
yotei hu b'zug shebikshuso, he can go out with the bell on
his garment. And what did we say the difference was? We said
that for a person they're both jewelry, so they should be okay,
but if it's on his neck it might fall off and if
it's in the garment and woven in it's not a problem. So
what issue does the גמרא gemara have with it now now that
we're talking without a knocker? Because the end of it says וזה
וזה מקבלין טומאה, v'zeh v'zeh mekablin tumah, it says they can become
טמא. tamei. So אי דלית ליה ענבל, ei delais lei inbol, if
it doesn't have a knocker, מי מקבלי טומאה, mi mekablei tumah, why
how does it become טמא? tamei? Now why not? It's jewelry, jewelry
can become טמא. tamei. But now the גמרא gemara says we're said
we're talking without a knocker. And that's why the בהמה behemah one
does not become does not become טמא tamei because it doesn't have
a knocker. With a knocker it would be טמא. tamei. Fine. So
we're talking without a knocker. So the person one also doesn't have
a knocker. But it says the person it does become טמא. tamei.
Why is that? So גמרא Gemara says ורמינהי, v'reminhi, let's see I
mean logically it does if it's jewelry, but let's see the question
the גמרא Gemara has. העושה זוגין למכתשת. ha'oseh zugin l'machteshet. Now this
is interesting because you get a little window into some of their
like realia. If you made bells for a pounder. Apparently you know
they'd pound spices and what a mortar and pestle and they believed
that I don't know maybe there's maybe there's some truth to it
I don't know but they believed that if nice sound or like
when you made sound as you were beating it, it would actually
improve the quality of the right, it would improve the quality the
quality. So therefore they had bells on the pounder so so as
they're pounding it's ringing and making this nice sound. Okay at least
that's what רש"י Rashi says. You could just say they just did
it you know just because it was nice without but anyway not
but okay so you have it on your on your mortar and
pestle. Or ולאריסה, ula'arisah, you have it on your baby's crib. You
have little bells to make some noise for your baby to play
with.
ולמטפחות ספרים, ulamatpechos sefarim, or on wrappers for for for books. Now
we have right, now רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean books, it
means ספרי תורה. sifrei Torah. And רש"י Rashi actually says so it's
talking about you've got a nice you know cover for your ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and you put bells on it. Okay so ולמטפחות
תינוקות, ulamatpechos tinokos, or for things that you
you know all these things what's their הלכה *halacha* in terms of
טומאה tumah, *tumah*? יש להם ענבל טמאים *yesh lahem inbal tme'im*
if they have knockers then they're טמאים *tme'im* then they're vessels and
they're making sound and they're functioning. אין להם ענבל טהורים *ein lahem
inbal tehorim* they don't have a knocker they're טהורים *tehorim*. Now ניטלו
ענבליהן *nitlu inbeleihen* if they had a knocker and now the knocker
was removed, remember the principle that it's hard to lose the status
of becoming טמא tamei, *tamei*? So if it started with a knocker
and now the knocker is removed, עדיין טומאתן עליהם *adayin tumatan aleihem*.
Then they retain their טומאה tumah, *tumah* their status either if they
were טמא tamei. *tamei* or their ability to become טמא tamei *tamei*
because they don't lose that status so easily. So anyway before before
we get to the issue of removing the knocker we've got to
resolve this problem. We said our case was without knockers. We said
for a person it becomes טמא tamei *tamei* presumably because it's ornament.
But here we're saying these things for the crib and all these
other types of little bells are only are only טמא tamei *tamei*
with a knocker. So what is it? Do you need a knocker
or not? So let's see what the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* answer is. הני
מילי בתינוק *hani mili betinok* when do you need a knocker? When
you're talking about like for an infant or for a child, the
scarf around the child or the crib. דלקלא עבידי ליה *delakala avidi
leh* that they're the only function it would have is to make
nice sounds either on the crib or on the scarf. That's and
without that it's not serving any function. אבל גדול תכשיט הוא לו
*aval gadol tachshit hu lo* but for an adult it's jewelry so
he they will wear bells even without the knockers because it just
looks nice אע״ג דלית ענבל *af al gav deleit inbal* even without
a knocker. So no big you know חידוש chiddush *chiddush* here. Yes,
without a knocker for a human it can become טמא tamei *tamei*.
Yes if it's in the case which it's worn for jewelry. In
a case where it's not worn for jewelry, then only with a
knocker is it considered to be functional,
is it considered a vessel and able to become טמא tamei, *tamei*.
Okay, but it is interesting that you could wear something even though
the function of the bell because having these little bells looks nice
around your neck. It just reminds me of a תשובה *teshuvah* that
רב משה *Rav Moshe* has relevant for our פרק *perek* not exactly
the same but analogous that you know it was asked about wearing
a watch without an עירוב *eiruv*. So what's the problem with a
watch without an עירוב *eiruv*? Well again you know not everything that
you wear is considered as we're seeing I mean although here we're
at the rabbinic level is considered to be clothing or jewelry. Right?
You know you could wear a knapsack and that's a burden. So
maybe when you wear a watch it's just a convenient way to
carry around a time maker with you. You know they used to
carry it in a pocket, you carry it on your wrist, but
it's a way of carrying something with you. It's not clothing, it's
not jewelry. So can you wear a watch without an עירוב *eiruv*?
So רב משה *Rav Moshe* said, well you can wear it if
you would wear it even if it weren't working. Because you know
because then it because then you're wearing it as a form of
jewelry. Now maybe you wouldn't wear that
if it weren't working.
Right. So you know you could argue that you're still wearing it
as jewelry but but even as jewelry you need it to be
working or else it's stupid to be wearing it. Right. So you
could make a distinction.
But anyway but anyway but the point is is that it just
the case of the bell reminds me of that. It's not working
it doesn't got to it doesn't have the stopper the but you're
still wearing it because it still looks nice and then it's considered
מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah. *mekabel tumah*.
שבת *Shabbos* case that you just mentioned.
Right adding it into jewelry. I know. Right exactly. Exactly. You lead
us in then...
Another interesting point at least for me is is incidental השמעת קול
*hashma'at kol* not a problem then because like you know for instance...
We're not that's what we're not talking about שבת *Shabbos*.
No I know I'm just asking. Oh.
Yeah so that's a quest- all right so I don't want to
get in- I mean it's sort of incidental, you're not trying to
make it, it's a small קול *kol* what what is the status
of השמעת קול *hashma'at kol*? There's two issues about it. One is
rabbinically you're not allowed to play a musical instrument. One would imagine
that if you're wearing something that has bells on it that you're
do- you know that might make some noise as you're putting it
on or as you're walking. But you but you know but that's
incidental that that's not the rabbinic prohibition of playing a musical instrument.
Is there a problem about not being השמעת קול *hashma'at kol* on
שבת *Shabbos*? That's a different question and may maybe yes maybe no
there's a lot of you know ambiguity about what exactly are the
parameters of השמעת קול *hashma'at kol*. Okay not really okay. אמר מר
*amar mar*. In a separate שיעור *shiur* on הלכות שבת *hilchos Shabbos*.
אמר מר *amar mar*. ניטלו ענבליהן *nitlu inbeleihen*. So now we've figured
out that for some cases they're only a vessel if they've got
their knocker but when the knocker it had a knocker and then
removed it retains its status. ניטלו ענבליהן עדיין טומאתן עליהן *nitlu inbeleihen
adayin tumatan aleihen*. They still are טמא *tamei* if they were טמא
*tamei* or they still are able to become טמא
*tamei*. They don't lose their status so easily. Now now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says למאי חזי *lemai chazi*. But what can you use
it for? Because you remember first of all there's two questions. One
is is that we said that things do lose their status with
שינוי מעשה *shinui ma'aseh* a physical change. And here you did a
physical change. You actually removed the knocker. That should be what you
need. And number two is is that even though normally things retain
their status that's assuming they are still functional. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says here if you're telling me that they're not used as
ornament for ba- for kids and they don't have the knocker how
could they still even if they were once טמא *tamei* how could
they retain the status if they're... completely not functional now. It's like
you had a vessel and it broke, it fell on the floor
or there got a hole in it. So nobody would say oh
it's hard to lose its status. Once it stops being functional it
changes the status. So the גמרא says, what do you use this
for without the knocker if it's for a child? So the גמרא
says, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, let's see what the answer is. הואיל
והדיוט יכול להחזירו. Ho'il v'hedyot yakhol lehakhziro.
So אביי Abaye says because it's not such a big חידוש to
put the knocker back in. So it's not really considered to have
been a changed object, right? If you remove it and put it
back in, and presumably you would do it like it sounds like
you could do it at various times when you didn't want it
to be making the sound, so you haven't really changed it. You
could just put it back in. So that's why it's still מקבל
טומאה. Okay, even a הדיוט hedyot could put it back in. I
should say by the way this principle הואיל והדיוט יכול להחזירו hedyot
yakhol lehakhziro is important, comes up in another place in שבת we
discussed, you know, a few weeks ago, issues about like fixing things
and you know, you know, like, you know, something like the stuffing
fell out of the pillow and putting it back in, and is
that like making a vessel or not, you know, or like, you
know, the temple falls off of your glasses and putting it back
on, and so on. Anyway, one of the- putting together this מנורה,
menorah, if you remember. So one of the things that the פוסקים
poskim talk about is whether הדיוט יכול להחזירו. hedyot yakhol lehakhziro. Like
how easy is it and trivial is it that anybody could just
put it back and then maybe that's a factor to consider that
it's not like making a vessel. So here that's what אביי Abaye
says here, הדיוט יכול להחזירו, hedyot yakhol lehakhziro, so it still has
its status.
Would it not be then considered broken? If you like broke it
in half?
Yeah, or if you- maybe, I don't know, maybe if you destroy-
maybe if you destroyed the knocker, maybe if you sealed off the
hole in which the knocker goes back in, it would be hard.
So anyway, מתיב רבא. Motiv Rava. So רבא Rava asks on this.
הזוג והענבל, Hazug v'ha'inbal, the bell and the knocker, חיבור, chibbur, are
connec- are considered connected. If they're together and you touch one, then
they both become טמא, okay, they're all one unit. So, now why
is that a question? Fine, they're one unit, but maybe when you
take them apart, it's still considered to be a vessel. So let's
take a look. וכי תימא הכי קאמר, V'khi teima hakhi ka'amar, this
is what it's saying, אף על גב דלא מחבר כמאן דמחבר דמי,
af al gav d'lo mekhabber k'man d'mekhabber dami, even when they're not
attached, it's like they're attached. והתניא, Ve'ha tanya, but one minute, we
taught in the ברייתא: baraita: מספורת של פרקים, Masporet shel perakim, you
remember- you might remember this, we had this a while ago, not
so long ago. If you have scissors that is made- that are
like- two blades? Yeah, two blades, I know, I'm just looking for
the words of like a- that you assemble, okay, that's made of
different components. ואיזמל של רהטני, Ve'izmel shel rehatni, or you've got a
carpenter's plane,
חיבור לטומאה, chibbur l'tumah, so they're made of two components, like a
carpenter's plane is the wood frame and the metal- the metal-like piece
in it. The scissors are the two blades. So, they're considered one
unit for becoming טמא. If you touch one of the blades, the
other becomes טמא when they're combined.
ואין חיבור להזאה, Ve'ein chibbur l'haza'ah, but if you're sprinkling the water
of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah on it, then if it touches
one blade, it's not like it touched the whole vessel. You have
to make the water touch the other blade. They're considered detached for
those purposes. So the גמרא says, we're not- let's first- let's first
flesh this out and see then how it's relevant. אמרינן מאי שנא,
Amrinan ma'i shna, we said what difference does it make? אי חיבור
הוא אפילו הזאה, I chibbur hu, afilu haza'ah,
if it's considered one unit, then even for sprinkling the ashes, when
it touches one it should be good.
ואי לא חיבור הוא אפילו לטומאה נמי, Ve'i lo chibbur hu, afilu
l'tumah nami, then for טומאה, then- then for טומאה, if it touches
one it should be like it didn't touch the other. Either it's
one unit or not one unit, make up your mind. גמרא says,
נמי לא. nami lo. So the גמרא says, ואמר רבא, ve'amar Raba,
so רבא Raba explains it in the following way. דבר תורה לא,
Devar Torah lo, biblically speaking, here's the difference. בשעת מלאכה, Bish'at melakhah,
if you're using the scissors, or it's the time of the scissors,
maybe you're not actually cutting right now but you're in the middle
of using them, you're doing sewing. So then, then חיבור, chibbur, then
it's considered one unit, because then you want it together, בין לטומאה
בין להזאה bein l'tumah bein l'haza'ah for all purposes, either becoming טמא
or becoming טהור. tahor. שלא בשעת מלאכה, Shelo bish'at melakhah,
now you're done sewing and what you would do when you were
done sewing is, you would take your scissors apart. It's not just
like you could in theory take them apart. The practice would be
when you're done doing it, you put it back into its compartment
and you take it apart. So now you're done sewing. You haven't
got around to taking it apart yet, but that's what's going to
happen. So in that case, so אינו חיבור לא לטומאה ולא להזאה,
eino chibbur lo l'tumah velo l'haza'ah, they're considered separate units even before
you took them apart. וגזרו על טומאה שלא בשעת מלאכה משום טומאה
שהיא בשעת מלאכה, Vegazru al tumah shelo bish'at melakhah mishum tumah shehi
bish'at melakhah, but what the rabbis said is, we have to rabbinically
be strict in both cases. So if it becomes טמא even when
you're done your sewing, we'll have to consider it one unit and
say if one becomes טמא the other does because we don't want-
people won't get this distinction, we have to be consistent. והזאה שבשעת
מלאכה משום הזאה שלא בשעת מלאכה, Ve'haza'ah shebish'at melakhah mishum haza'ah shelo
bish'at melakhah, and then the reverse for sprinkling. The sprinkling is making
it טהור. tahor. So if we want to be strict about sprinkling,
we're going to have to say for sprinkling purposes, we'll always consider
it to be like two units. Okay, so the basic answer is
that rabbinically we're strict in both cases whether it is the time
when you're doing the מלאכה or not the time when you're doing
the מלאכה. So being strict means it'll always become טמא, one unit,
and it'll be harder to become טהור tahor for טהור tahor purposes.
It needs to be if they're considered separate units. Now, how is
any of this relevant to אביי's Abaye answer about whether you can
put the knocker back into the, back into the bell? So תוספות
Tosafot says it's really quite simple because all of this says that
at what stage biblically speaking is it considered to be טהור? tahor?
When is it these scissors, when are they considered separate units rather,
these scissors, at what stage? When it's שלא בשעת מלאכה. shelo bish'at
melacha. Okay, and certainly once you've disassembled them, they are considered separate
units. So אביי Abaye says how can רבא Rava say that it's
all considered still one vessel and therefore it doesn't lose its status
if when if we say that as soon as it's not being
used and it's and it's sort of in the position which where
you're going to take it apart, it's considered two vessels, and how
much more so once you've already taken it apart?
Okay, once you remove the clapper from the bell.
So you remove the clapper from the bell, it's certainly considered to
be two separate vessels and therefore that should change the status. Okay,
so that's אביי's Abaye question. So let's see what the answer is.
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, I'm sorry, excuse me, why did
I say אביי's Abaye question? That's רבא's Rava question on אביי. Abaye.
That's רבא's Rava challenge of אביי. Abaye. So אלא אמר רבא, Ella
amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava said, הואיל וראוי להקישו על גבי
חרס פיצי. ho'il vera'uy lehakkisho al gabbei cheres pizi. Who needs a
stopper for a bell? You can bang the bell on a piece
of pottery and use something else as, you know, you know what
of course a kid's favorite toy is. It's, you know, the wooden
ladle and a pot, right? So, so he says, so of course
you can still use it. So even without the stopper, if it
wasn't, if it never had the stopper in it, so you're not
done making it. You're only done making it when you put in
the stopper. But once it's had the stopper in it, it's considered
a bell even without the stopper because you can still bang it
and make noise with it. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, and we taught
also, אמר רבי יוחנן ורבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi Chanina, הואיל
וראוי להקישו על גבי חרס, ho'il vera'uy lehakkisho al gabbei cheres, because
you can bang it on pottery. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer,
הואיל וראוי לגמע בו מים לתינוק. ho'il vera'uy ligmei bo mayim letinok.
No, you can use it as a scooper to, you know, to
like a cymbal, to put for to give water to a child
or to an infant. So he says, and this is going to
be the discussion tomorrow, you have a vessel that was usable. It
now changed, physically changed, and you can't use it in its original
function but you can use it in a different function. So you
can't use it as a bell, רבא Rava says you could still
use it as a bell, fine. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
you're not going to use it as a bell anymore but you
could use it for some other function. Will it still be considered
a vessel for purposes of טומאה וטהרה? tumah vetaharah? Will it still
retain its status as being as being a vessel if once it
had that status? So we will find out more about this tomorrow.